Guide to the Trent history of medicine manuscripts collection, [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Trent History of Medicine manuscript collection [1588?], 1661-1994 and undated, bulk 1750-1980, (780 collections; approximately 6,000 items)
  - Beck, Theodric Romeyn, 1791-1855. Letter, [Between 1815 and 1840], (1 item) (Box 1)
    Physician and professor of medicine, of New York State. Letter (ALS). Requests of Mr. Little, a book dealer, the account against the Western College of Physicians and Surgeons for various medical journals.
  - Béclard, Jules, 1817-1887. Letter, 1869, Sept. 17, (1 item) (Box 1)
    Physician and professor of physiology, Paris. Letter (ALS) relating to a request for a letter of recommendation.
  - Behn, Wilhelm Friedrich Georg, 1808-1878. Letters, 1855-1869, (6 items) (Box 1)
    German professor of anatomy and zoology, Kiel. Six letters (ALS). Writes to direct the handling of botanical and zoological specimens collected during a scientific expedition to India and America, made by Behn and Danish scientists on the warship "Galathea". Two letters give an account of the controversy connected to his appointment to the Leopold-Charles' Academy in Dresden.
  - Behring, Emil von, 1854-1917. Letters, 1896-1897, (4 items) (Box 1)
    German biochemist. Three letters (ALS) and a postcard, signed. Correspondence relates to their work with toxoids, inactivated toxins which retain the property of stimulating antitoxin formation and which are used in immunization.
  - Bell, Charles, Sir, 1774-1842. Papers, 1830 and undated, (8 items) (Box 1)
    British surgeon and anatomist. Letter (ALS) dated Oct. 20, 1830 tendering his resignation as Professor of Physiology at the University of London; a pencil sketch and engravings of drawings by Bell; a copy of a portrait of Bell by J. Stevens and two clippings.
  - Bell, Jacob, d. 1859. Papers, 1840-1859 and undated, (5 items) (Box 2)
    English chemist and founder of the Pharmaceutical Society. Two clippings, a note (ANS), and a letter (ALS) to William Hookham Carpenter. A note to Carpenter from Edwin Landseer is on the inside page of the letter. Another letter to W. H. Brotherton advises that Brotherton prepare a defense and recommends the services of a George Brace, Bell's solicitor as well as solicitor of the Pharmaceutical Society.
  - Bell, John, 1763-1820. Letter, [1795 Aug.], (1 item) (Box 2)
    Scottish surgeon. Letter (ALS). Writes to London bookseller, Mr. Bell, in regard to "this" book, probably his Engravings of the Bones, Muscles, and Joints.
  - Bell, John, 1796-1872. Letter, 1831, Dec., (2 items) (Box 2)
    Philadelphia surgeon. Manuscript (43 p.) and letter (ALS). Manuscript "Observations on cholera," by Bell and dedicated to Chelius, is accompanied by letter, originally tipped into the ms.
  - Bérard, Auguste, 1802-1846. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 2)
    French surgeon and professor of surgery, Paris. Note (ANS) to "Mon cher confrère." Requests meeting.
  - Bérard, Pierre Honeré, 1802-1846. Letter, undated, (1 item) (Box 2)
    French professor of physiology, Paris. Letter (ALS). Reminds the addressee of his promise to write a chapter on the anatomy of the lungs and throat for a book Bérard is preparing to publish.
  - Berg, Janüs Anton Rahbek. Papers, 1909 and undated, (2 items) (Box 2)
    Letter (ALS), dated 1909, June 9, from Berg to the University Library in Copenhagen is accompanied by manuscript notes on Berg in an anonymous hand.
  - Bergh, Rudolph, 1824-1909. Papers, 1853-1907, (110 items) (Box 2)
    Danish venereologist, dermatologist and comparative anatomist. Correspondence, certificates and manuscript notes, in Danish, French and German. Correspondents include Herman Lynge, F. Didrichsen, and Franz Leydig. Bergh received an appointment as correspondent member to the French Academy of Sciences in 1895 from M.P.E. Berthelot. Most of the material relates to his study of Nudibranchiata, a sub-order of marine gastropod mollusks.
  - Bergmann, Ernst von, 1836-1907. Letter, [Before 1907], (1 item) (Box 2)
    German-Russian surgeon. Letter, undated [before 1907], written from Berlin.
  - Bernard, Claude, 1813-1878. Letters, 1867-1871, (2 items) (Box 2)
    French physiologist. Two letters (ALS). One letter congratulates M. Devilliers upon receipt of an award, while another provides a recommendation for M. Vinot, a medical student.
  - Bert, Paul, 1833-1886. Note, [Between 1880 and 1886], (2 items) (Box 2)
    French physiologist and civil servant. Note (ANS) relating to a memorial. Includes transcription.
  - Berthelot, Marcellin, 1827-1907. Letter, 1888, Dec. 9, (1 item) (Box 2)
    French chemist and politician. Letter (ALS) on the preventive fire-proofing of theaters.
  - Bethune, Norman. Papers, 1970-1976 and undated, (12 items) (Box 2)
    Canadian physician, 1890-1939. Newspaper clippings and letters (LS). Bethune worked in China in the late 1930s and the clippings document renewed interest in Bethune in early 1970s as relations improved between China and the West. Correspondence consists of inquiries regarding Bethune from R.J. Stewart to J.L. Wilson.
  - Biddle, Nicholas, 1786-1844. Letters, 1817-1840 and undated, (5 items) (Box 2)
    Writer, politician and financier, of Pennsylvania. Four letters (ALS) addressed to Biddle from Caspar Wistar, Robert Hare and Nathaniel Chapman. Wistar writes regarding quarantine regulations, that, on the one hand, they should prevent the introduction of contagious diseases and, on the other, should not be "burdensome to commerce". Includes transcription of Wistar letter.
  - Bigelow, Henry Jacob, 1818-1890. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Surgeon of Boston, Massachusetts. Note (ANS) informing addressee of his return.
  - Bigelow, Jacob, 1786-1879. Letter, 1822-1833, (2 items) (Box 2)
    Physician and botanist of Boston, Mass. Letter (ALS) to Loammi Baldwin and a holograph document, signed, noting receipt of $12.00 from the proprietors of Mount Auburn Cemetery.
  - Billings, John Shaw, 1838-1913. Letters, 1891, Apr. 13 and May 13, (2 items) (Box 2)
    U.S. Army surgeon and founder of the Army Medical Library. Two letters (TLS). Billings, as Director of the New York Public Library, makes bids for some documents and manuscripts offered by Benjamin to the Library.
  - Bios, J. B. Note, 1853, July 27, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Note (ANS) with instructions for purchase of stock.
  - Bischoff, Theodor Ludwig Wilhelm, 1807-1882. 1873, May 12, (3 items) (Box 2)
    German comparative anatomist and physiologist. Photograph, letter (ALS), and signature sample.
  - Björnsson, Gümund. Letters, 1913, Jan. 30, (2 items) (Box 2)
    Letter (ALS), placing an order with the bookseller for purchase of books from the private library of Prof. Wimmer. Includes transcription.
  - Blackwell, Elizabeth, 1821-1910. Papers, 1849-1863 and undated, (4 items) (Box 2)
    First U.S. woman to receive a medical degree. Two letters (ALS), a printed calling card, and a photo of an newspaper column containing biographical information. In one letter, Blackwell writes to William Robert Prince regarding his work in horticulture.
  - Blainville, Henri-Marie Ducrotay, 1777-1850. Note, 1846, [Oct.] 21, (1 item) (Box 2)
    French zoologist and comparative anatomist. Note (ANS).
  - Blanche, Antoine Émile, b. 1828. Letter, 1882, Aug. 21, (2 items) (Box 2)
    French psychiatrist. Letter (ALS) to a colleague about a patient, the husband of a Madame Serac. Includes transcription.
  - Blanche, Esprit Sylvestre, 1796-1852. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 2)
    French psychiatrist. Dinner invitation (ANS).
  - Bland-Sutton, John, Sir, 1855-1936. Papers, 1889-1899, (46 items; one folder, one flat box) (Box 2)
    English surgeon and gynecologist. Most of the material relates to the leasing of property by Bland-Sutton, in particular correspondence with his solicitor, Edward John Quintas Maggs, regarding a case against Bland-Sutton, brought by a Mrs. Heath, regarding a sublet property. Other material relates to the alteration of his surname from Sutton to Bland-Sutton. Oversize materials are in separate 11x14 inch box at the Library Service Center, Box 1 (see library catalog record for Bland-Sutton).
  - Blizzard, William, Sir, 1743-1835. Letter, 1816, June 27, ( 1 item) (Box 2)
    English surgeon. Letter (ALS) referring to various financial matters.
  - Blue, Rupert Lee, 1868-1948. 1919, Jan. 10, (1 item) (Box 2)
    U.S. physician, Surgeon General of the U.S. Public Health Service between 1912-1920. Letter (TLS), with regrets that he will be unable to attend the annual banquet of the Order of Washington.
  - Blumenthal, Cellier de. Papers, 1870 and undated, (8 items) (Box 2)
    Head of the voluntary nurses of the third district during the siege of Paris by the Prussians in 1870. Two letters (ALS) relating to Blumenthal's efforts to address allegations by a group of women that she is a Prussian. Includes transcription and translation of both letters.
  - Blundell, Dr., 1790-1878. Document, 1848, May 4, (1 item) (Box 2)
    James Blundell, English physician, lecturer on midwifery and physiology. Holograph, signed. A prescription.
  - Bond, Thomas, 1712-1784. Letter, 1773, Aug. 28, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician of Philadelphia. Letter (ALS) prescribing a course of treatment for Pemberton's daily attacks of fever.
  - Borland, J. Nelson. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Note (ANS) from Boston.
  - Bouillaud, Jean, 1796-1881. Note, 1848, Oct. 17, (2 items) (Box 2)
    French physician and civil servant. Note (ANS) informing the mayor that the Chemical Amphitheatre will be available at the requested date and time. Includes translation.
  - Bowditch, Henry Ingersoll, 1808-1892. Letter, 1882, Apr. 7, (1 item) (Box 2)
    U.S. specialist in diseases of the chest. Letter (ALS) regarding a case of sudden death immediately following and apparently caused by aspiration of the chest witnessed by McMurtry at the Charity Hospital of New Orleans in 1873 or 1874.
  - Bowen, Ephraim, 1710-1808. Letter, 1807, June 10, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician of Rhode Island. Letter (ALS) informing the Governor of a small balance due from the Governor's grandfather, Arthur Fenner. On the address side is a note in the Governor's hand.
  - Bradfield, Henry Joseph Steele, 1805-1852. Letters, 1843-1845, (22 items) (Box 2)
    English surgeon and colonial officer. 18 letters (ALS). Bradfield writes Philippart regarding manuscripts submitted for publication in the United Service Journal and regarding his financial difficulties, which followed upon his release from the colonial service for quarreling with another officer. Includes translations of six of the letters.
  - Bradford, William, 1729-1808. Document, [1765, Dec. 13], (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician, lawyer and legislator of Rhode Island. Holograph, signed. A statement of payments past due on Bourn's account.
  - Braun, Alexander, 1805-1877. Note, 1800s, Feb. 20, (1 item) (Box 2)
    German botanist. Note (ANS) inviting Gilman to an evening with the "Gesellschaft naturforscher Freunde."
  - Brayton, Charles E. Papers, 1892-1909 and undated, (57 items) (Box 2)
    Physician of Stonington, Connecticut. These documents were separated from Brayton's ledger books, 1882-1913, which have been catalogued separately. One group consists of receipts of purchase and medical supply company contracts. A second group relates to Brayton's efforts to collect on delinquent accounts through the employment of various collection agencies, including the National Mercantile Company, the Whitney Law Corporation, and Everett A. Kingsley.
  - Breschet, Gilbert, 1784-1845. Papers, 1825-1831 and undated, (4 items) (Box 2)
    French physician and anatomist. Three letters (ALS). Breschet places a subscription to Cuvier's work on fishes with a M. Lerrault. In a letter to Breschet, J. Cruveilhier expresses discontent with his situation in Montpellier.
  - Brewster, David, Sir, 1781-1868. Papers, 1836-1857, (3 items) (Box 2)
    Scottish physicist. Three notes (ANS).
  - Brigham, Amariah, 1798-1849. Letter, 1843, June 6, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician of New York. Letter (ALS). As Director of the New York State Lunatic Asylum, Brigham writes with news about the affairs of and events at the Asylum.
  - Bright, Richard, 1789-1858. Papers, undated, (4 items) (Box 2)
    English physician and pathologist. Two notes (ANS) and two holograph notes, unsigned, relating to various social engagements.
  - Broadbent, William Henry, Sir, 1835-1907. Note, 1900, Sept., (1 item) (Box 2)
    English physician. Holograph inscription, signed. Broadbent's compliments to Dr. H. Barton Jacobs, on the fly-leaf of a copy of the third edition of Broadbent's book on heart disease, presented to Jacobs. Attached is a note in Jacobs' hand.
  - Broca, Paul, 1824-1880. Papers, 1869 and undated, (4 items) (Box 2)
    French surgeon. Note (ANS) with regards to a course of treatment, and a letter (ALS) discussing, among other things, artificial limbs. Includes transcriptions of both items, and a translation of the letter (ALS).
  - Brodie, Benjamin, Sir, 1783-1862. Papers, 1821-1862 and undated, (9 items) (Box 2)
    English surgeon. 8 letters (ALS) and a note (ANS). Correspondence includes a letter to his brother, W. B. Brodie regarding his health, a letter of recommendation for Dr. Seth Thompson, and a letter to Daniel Ellis regarding the election to the Royal Society of the physician and physiologist Alexander Philips Wilson Philip, nominated by chemist and physicist William Hyde Wollaston and others. Other letters and notes relate to patients and treatments. A transcription of the letter to Ellis is included.
  - Brooks, John, 1752-1825. Documents, 1819-1821, (2 items) (Box 2)
    Physician and Governor of Massachusetts, 1816-1823. Two documents, signed, appointing Henry Adams as Coroner of Norfolk County and John Rollins as Division Inspector of the Second Division of the Militia. Both documents are also signed by Alden Bradford, as Secretary of the Commonwealth.
  - Brouardel, Paul, 1837-1906. Letter, 1883, Nov. 11, (3 items) (Box 2)
    French physician. Letter (ALS) regarding the transport of various anatomical specimens across the French-German border. Includes transcription and translation.
  - Broussais, Casimir Anne Marie, 1803-1847. Letter, 1820, July 15, (3 items) (Box 2)
    French physician and phrenologist. Letter (ALS), referring a patient to Dr. Husson's care. Includes transcription and translation.
  - Broussais, François Joseph Victor, 1772-1838. Letter, 1818-1837, (3 items) (Box 2)
    French physician, military physician, and professor of pathology, University of Paris. Letter (ALS) and a document, signed. Both related to military matters. Includes translation of the letter.
  - Brown, Buckminster, 1819-1891. Letter, 1856, Apr. 5, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Orthopedic surgeon, of Boston. Letter (ALS) to Peabody, editor of the "North American Review", regarding his article "The poetry of anatomy."
  - Brown, George, 1755-1822. Letter, 1808, June 7, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician, of Baltimore. Holograph, signed. Attests that William Patterson, Jr., cannot serve in the military due to his physical and mental condition. Also signed by Colin Mackenzie.
  - Brown, Gustavus, b. 1744. Letter, 1787, Mar. 19, (1 item) (Box 2)
    Physician, of Maryland. Letter (ALS) regarding the estate of his wife, Mary (Reeder) Ireland Brown, daughter of Colonel John Reeder.
  - Brown, Horace Manchester, 1857-1929. letter, 1927, Apr. 11, (1 item) (Box 3)
    U.S. surgeon. Letter (LS). Reports failure to discover an English translation of "Luzumiyat" by the Arab poet Alu'l-Ala, who lived from 973 to 1055.
  - Brown, John, 1810-1882. Papers, 1816-1881 and undated, (11 items) (Box 3)
    Scottish physician. A collection of letters (ALS) from Brown, including a letter from Brown's grandfather, the Rev. John Brown; photostats, including one of the first page of the first edition of Brown's "Horae subsecivae"; and holograph notes in an anonymous hand.
  - Brown, Robert, 1773-1858. Manuscript, [After 1826], (1 item) (Box 3)
    Scottish physician. Holograph, unsigned. A memorial to Dr. Clarke Abel.
  - Brown-Séquard, Charles-Edouard, 1817-1894. Papers, 1871-1889 and undated, (6 items) (Box 3)
    French physiologist, neurologist and endocrinologist. Letters (ALS), in French and English, relating to professional matters and prescribing treatments, and a portrait of Brown-Séquard.
  - Buchan, William, 1729-1805. Papers, 1773-1801, (6 items) (Box 3)
    Scottish physician. Letters (ALS), including instructions for the third edition of Buchan's "Domestic Medicine". In the same letter he also relates anecdotes of incidents in which people made use of the book's medical advice. A letter to Cadell and Davies (booksellers and publishers) concerns his Medical advice to mothers and his Treatise on venereal disease. This letter was removed from the Thomas Cadell collection. A holograph note, in an anonymous hand, provides biographical information.
  - Buchanan, George, Sir, 1831-1895. Letter, 1863, Nov. 4, (1 item) (Box 3)
    English sanitarian. Letter (ALS) to H. S. Scott in the course of his inquiry into the "state of Public Vaccination in London."
  - Buchez, Philippe-Joseph-Benjamin, 1796-1865. Letter, 1861, Jan. 28, (2 items) (Box 3)
    French physician. Letter (ALS) to his publisher. Apologizes for not having fulfilled his obligations and promises to start work on his book the following week. Includes transcription and translation.
  - Bull, William Tillinghast, 1849-1909. Letter, 1893, May 3, (1 item) (Box 3)
    Surgeon, of New York City. Letter (ALS). Thanks Mrs. Doremus for the kindness and sympathy shown to him and Mrs. Bull. Written on stationery from New York City's Plaza Hotel.
  - Bumgarner, John Reed. Letter, 1945, Nov. 24, (1 item) (Box 3)
    North Carolina physician. This typed transcript copy of a letter from Bumgarner to Davison, made for Mrs. Trent, was removed from the "Bataan" copy of Davison's Compleat Pediatrician, a volume in the Duke History of Medicine Collection, call number "II Davison". The letter relates that Bumgarner made much use of the book during the WWII campaign in the Pacific.
  - Burnett, George, 1776?-1811. Letter, 1810, June 5, (1 item) (Box 3)
    English military surgeon and writer. Letter (ALS) to the editor or publisher of the "Annual Register" soliciting an assignment.
  - Burnham, Walter, 1808-1883. Letter, 1882, May 11, (1 item) (Box 3)
    Gynecologist, of Lowell. Letter (ALS) to his editor or publisher, asking for paper to finish his autobiography.
  - Burr, Aaron, 1756-1836. Letter, 1793, Dec. 24, (4 items) (Box 3)
    U.S. politician and lawyer. Letter (ALS) to Mrs. Burr informing her that Benjamin Rush, uninformed that she is already taking hemlock for her illness, advises the same. Includes transcription.
  - Busse, Ewald W., 1917. Manuscript, [Between 1942 and 1947], (32 items) (Box 3)
    Duke University gerontologist. Busse's holograph translation of sections from Alois Eduard Kornmüller's "Einführung in die klinische Elektrenkephalographie." Accompanied by an 11-page typescript of holograph translation. Both were received as part of Busse's gift of a copy of Kornmüller's book to the History of Medicine Collections.
  - Cabanis, Pierre Jean Georges, 1757-1808. Letter, 1803, Feb. 5 or 6, (1 item) (Box 3)
    French physician, physiologist and materialist philosopher. Letter (ALS). In this very cordial letter, apparently written to Maine de Biran after his exclusion from the Council of Five Hundred on suspicion of royalism, Cabanis, himself a member of the Council, admonishes him to continue with his work, promising him every assistance.
  - Cabell, James Lawrence, 1813-1889. Papers, 1876-1877, (3 items) (Box 3)
    Confederate hospital head, professor and chairman of the faculty at the University of Virginia. Notes (ANS) instructing the proctor to pay the monthly salaries of two infirmary employees.
  - Cadell, Thomas, 1773-1836. Letters, 1783-1817 and undated, (9 items) (Box 3)
    London publisher and bookseller. Letters (ALS) to Thomas Cadell, Sr. (1742-1802), Thomas, Jr., and William Davies (d. 1820), publishers and booksellers, from James Makittrick Adair, regarding his essay on regimen; from John Aikin; from George Armstrong, regarding his Essay on the diseases most fatal to infants; from Alexander Peter Buchan, regarding a book on sea-bathing; from Thomas Cogan, regarding his Theological Disquisitions; from Quintin Craufurd; from James Currie; from William Hey, regarding his Practical Observations in Surgery, and from Benjamin Rumford, regarding the second edition of his Seventh Essay. A letter written by William Buchan was removed from this collection and placed with the William Buchan collection.
  - Caldwell, Charles, 1772-1853. Letters, 1816-1838, (2 items) (Box 3)
    Surgeon and professor of medicine. Letter (ALS) to Nahum Capen, restating the argument of Caldwell's book, Phrenology Vindicated, and Anti-Phrenology Unmasked, and a letter (ALS) to Reverend Samuel Gilman, relating to personal matters.
  - Campbell, Alexander, 1779-1857. Note, 1808, Apr. 14, (1 item) (Box 3)
    U.S. physician and Congressman of Ohio. Holograph, signed. Promissory note for forty-five dollars to be paid to Joseph Basset.
  - Camper, Petrus, 1722-1789. Letter, 1786, Oct. 9, (6 items) (Box 3)
    Dutch physician, anatomist and naturalist. Letters (ALS). Typescript of French original and typed English translation are available. Discusses the petrified fossils of Montmartre, Maestricht, and Euhstedt and the cetaceans at M. de Buffon's in Paris. Expresses disappointment at being unable to see Goethe, touching on the troubled internal political affairs of the Netherlands. Announces intention to make a short trip to Germany in the spring in order to visit Merck and Soemmerring.
  - Cappel, Wilhelm Friedrich, 1734-1800. Manuscript, c. 1779, (1 item) (Box 3)
    German physician and professor at the University of Helmstadt. Holograph, signed.
  - Carlyle, John Aitken, 1801-1879. Letters, 1840 and [Between 1843 and 1854], (2 items) (Box 3)
    Scottish physician and scholar. Letter (ALS) to Anthony Panizzi, regarding Panizzi's articles on Rosetti and Boniface, and to Archibald Glen, placing an order for a book, Davis' Chinese.
  - Carnochan, John Murray, 1817-1887. Letters, 1867-1876 and undated, (4 items) (Box 3)
    Physician of New York. Three letters (ALS) to Seaver relating to personal and professional matters.
  - Carro, Joannes de, 1770-1857. Note, undated, (1 item) (Box 3)
    Physician of Geneva, practiced in Vienna, Prague and Carlsbad. Note (ANS). Expects a good season in Carlsbad.
  - Carus, Carl Gustav, 1789-1869. Letter, 1836, June 12, (1 item) (Box 3)
    German physiologist and psychologist. Note (ANS). Recommends a Mr. Falkenstein, Librarian to the King of Saxony, to Cuvier.
  - Castellani, Aldo, 1875-1971. Letters, 1950-1956, (2 items) (Box 3)
    Italian physician; specialized in tropical medicine. Letters (ALS, TLS) relating to sample bacterial cultures sent by Castellani to Smith.
  - Castiglioni, Arturo, 1874-1953. Papers, 1941 and undated, (3 items) (Box 3)
    Italian born professor of medicine and history of medicine, Yale University. Letter (ALS) from Castiglioni to Josiah Trent and two clippings of reviews of the English translation, History of Medicine, of Castiglioni's Storia della Medicina.
  - Chancellor, William, d. 1762. Document, 1762, Dec. 13 and 20, (1 item) (Box 3)
    Physician, of Philadelphia. An inventory of Chancellor's estate, in four parts: medicines, medical instruments, books, and personal and household goods.
  - Chantemesse, André, 1851-1919. Note, 1886, Apr. 8, (2 items) (Box 3)